Preliminary Guide to the Augustus Jay DuBois Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Augustus Jay DuBois papers
1869-1913
MS 931
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
Correspondence, engineering notebooks, lectures, and manuscripts on engineering, poems, plays, newspaper clippings, and other printed matter. The correspondence is chiefly on engineering, but also contains three notes from Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr. discussing science and religion. All of DuBois' poems and plays also deal with the topics of science and religion. Also included is his unpublished manuscript: Mechanics of Engineering.
DuBois, A. J. (Augustus Jay), 1849-1915
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift to Yale University in 1937.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Augustus J. DuBois papers, 1869-1913, consist of three linear feet of correspondence, writings, and printed matter related to his teaching and writing. The correspondence, consisting mostly of incoming letters, is mainly concerned with engineering, but there are also three notes from Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr., acknowledging and commenting on DuBois's writings on science and religion. The writings consist of notes, manuscripts, and typescripts of DuBois's poems and plays, his lectures, and his published and unpublished works on engineering and the relation between science and religion. The printed matter is mainly reprints and clippings.
Biographical / Historical
Augustus Jay DuBois, Ph.B. 1869, C.E. 1870, Ph.D. 1873. Assistant in Field Engineering 1874-1875; Higgin Professor of Dynamic Engineering 1877-1884; Professor of Civil Engineering 1884-1915, author of Elements of Mechanics.
[ Historical Register of Yale University, 1701-1937]
Engineering; Religion and science; Civil engineers; Educators; Engineers; DuBois, A. J. (Augustus Jay), 1849-1915; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School. Dept. of Civil Engineering
- Inventory
  - Correspondence (A-Z), 1873-1897 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript notebooks
    - "The New Haven Water Works", 1869 (Box 2)
    - "A Comparison of a Few of the Combinations Used in the Construction of Bridges", 1870 (Box 2)
    - "An Investigation of the Strains in Framed Structures...", 1872 (Box 2)
    - The Elements of Graphical Statistics, 1876 (Box 3–4)
    - The Elements of Graphical Statistics: Atlas and Index, 1876 (Box 5)
  - Engineering notebooks, undated (Box 5)
  - Manuscript notebooks (translations by A. J. DuBois)
    - "Fall of Solid Bodies in a Liquid" by Ritter von Rittinger, 1869 (Box 6)
    - "Graphical Statistics" by Gustav Zeuner, [1869?] (Box 6)
    - Outline of the Mechanical Theory of Heat by Gustav Zeuner, 1873 (Box 6)
  - Mechanics of Engineering, vol. 2: manuscript, 1902 (Box 7)
  - Lecture manuscripts
    - "The Early History of the Steam Engine", 1879 (Box 8)
    - "The Story of a Lighthouse": manuscript and typescript, [1880?] (Box 8)
    - "Work and Heat," parts I and II, 1883 (Box 8)
    - "Geology vs. Astronomy", undated (Box 8)
  - Poems and plays, undated (Box 8)
    - "Science and Faith": manuscript and reprint, 1881, 1892 (Box 9)
    - "Science and the Spiritual": manuscript and reprint, 1886, 1887 (Box 9)
    - "Science and Miracle": manuscript and typescript, [1888?] (Box 9)
    - "Science and Religion": manuscript, [1890?] (Box 9)
    - "The Religion of a Scientist": typescript, 1905 (Box 9)
    - "Science and the Supernatural": manuscript and reprint, 1890, 1908 (Box 9)
    - "The Religion of a Civil Engineer": reprint, 1913 (Box 9)
    - "Science and Immortality": manuscript, undated (Box 9)
    - Poems by various authors: typescripts, undated (Box 10)
    - Notebook containing newspaper and magazine clippings and mathematics notes, 1875-1880 (Box 11)
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings, notes, and miscellaneous printed matter, 1879, 1882, 1886 (Box 11)